Green, William Papers on Microfilm 5761 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
William Green Papers on Microfilm
1891-1956
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Green, William
5761 mf
2.33 cubic feet
21 microfilm reels
Diaries, speeches (documents), microfilm.
Correspondents of note include Mother Jones, George Meany, Matthew Woll, Daniel Tobin, President Woodrow Wilson, President Franklin D. Roosevelt, and officers of the United Mine Workers of America.
3337356
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 26, 2012
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 02, 2019
Biographical / Historical
William Green (March 3, 1873 November 21, 1952)
After eight years of formal schooling, William Green began work in the coal mines of Ohio at age sixteen. Two years later, Green became secretary of the Coshocton Progressive Miners Union, which later became a local of the United Mine Workers of America. Green proceeded to hold a series of offices in the UMWA, including a ten year tenure as UMWA international secretary treasurer after an unsuccessful campaign for the UMWA presidency in 1910. Green served two terms in the Ohio Senate, where he wrote that state's workmen's compensation act. In 1914, he became a fourth vice-president and member of the Executive Council of the American Federation of Labor. Upon the death of Samuel Gompers in 1924, Green became president of the AFL and continued to hold that post until his death in 1952.
Green was successful in acquiring federation support for a national unemployment insurance system sponsored largely by employer donations. In 1935 he facilitated the passage of the National Labor Relations Act, to help empower workers' rights to organize and to take part in collective bargaining. Green helped pass the Fair Labor Standards Act, in 1938, which became the first federal law in instituting minimum wages and the 40-hour workweek.
Scope and Contents
Correspondents of note include Mother Jones, George Meany, Matthew Woll, Daniel Tobin, President Woodrow Wilson, President Franklin D. Roosevelt, and officers of the United Mine Workers of America.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5402 mf: Correspondence of American Federation of Labor President William Green on Microfilm 5431 mf: Letterpress Copybooks of Samuel Gompers and William Green, Presidents on Microfilm 5431 mf: Letterpress Copybooks of Samuel Gompers and William Green, Presidents on Microfilm
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence and memoranda
Series II: Expense reports
Series III: Speeches and statements
Series IV: Subject files
Depressions -- 1929 -- United States; Labor unions -- United States -- Officials and employees; Labor unions and communism -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Economic aspects -- United States; Labor leaders; Coal mining industry -- United States -- State supervision; Mine safety -- Law and legislation -- United States; Nationalization -- Railroads -- United States; Plumb Plan; Strikes and lockouts -- Coal mining industry -- United States; Labor unions -- United States -- Corrupt practices; Unemployment insurance -- United States; Workers' compensation -- Law and legislation -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees; n Jones, Mother, 1837-1930; Green, William, 1872-1952; Lewis, John L. (John Llewellyn), 1880-1969; Meany, George, 1894-1980; Murray, Philip, 1886-1952; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Tobin, Daniel J. (Daniel Joseph), 1875-1955; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Woll, Matthew, 1880-1956.; American Federation of Labor; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); United Mine Workers of America; United States. Labor Management Relations Act, 1947; United States. National Labor Relations Act
3337356
- Series I: Correspondence and memoranda
  - 5 SEP 1909-27 DEC 1911, 1909-1911; 1 (Reel 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Material from Box 1: Folder 1.
  - 17 JAN 1912-15 OCT 1915, 2 JAN 1916, 1912-1916; 2 (Reel 1)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 2.
  - 1 NOV 1916-23 APR 1917, 1916-1917; 3 (Reel 1)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 3.
  - 1 MAY 1917-[pre 14 APR 1918], 1917-1918; 4 (Reel 1)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 4.
  - 2 MAY 1919-30 DEC 1919, 5 (Reel 1)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 5.
  - 1 JAN 1920-31 JUL 1920, 6 (Reel 1)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 6.
  - 1 AUG 1920-15 OCT 1920, 1 (Reel 2)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 7.
  - 17 OCT 1920-23 FEB 1921, 1920-1921; 2 (Reel 2)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 8.
  - 5 MAR 1921-[ca. 1921-1928?], 3 (Reel 2)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 9.
  - 4 JAN 1922-[1922?], 4 (Reel 2)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 10.
  - 1 JAN 1923-29 DEC 1923, 1 (Reel 3)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 11.
  - 10 JAN 1924-14 NOV 1924, 2 (Reel 3)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 12.
  - 17 DEC 1924-20 DEC 1924, 3 (Reel 3)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 13.
  - 21 DEC 1924-23 DEC 1924, 4 (Reel 3)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 14.
  - 24 DEC 1924-31 DEC 1924, 1 (Reel 4)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 15.
  - 1 JAN 1925-7 JAN 1925, 2 (Reel 4)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 16.
  - 8 JAN 1925-30 JAN 1925, 3 (Reel 4)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 17.
  - 1 FEB 1925-28 APR 1925, 1 (Reel 5)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 18.
  - 2 MAY 1925-31 OCT 1925, 2 (Reel 5)
    Material from Box 1: Folder 19.
  - 2 NOV 1925-[post FEB 1926], 1925-1926; 3 (Reel 5)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 1.
  - 2 MAR 1926-[1926?], 1 (Reel 6)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 2.
  - 1 JAN 1927-31 MAY 1927, 2 (Reel 6)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 3.
  - 1 JUN 1927-29 FEB 1928, 1927-1928; 3 (Reel 6)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 4.
  - 1 MAR 1928-DEC 1928, 4 (Reel 6)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 5.
  - 2 JAN 1929-31 DEC 1929, 1 (Reel 7)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 6.
  - 1 JAN 1930-31 DEC 1930, 2 (Reel 7)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 7.
  - 4 JAN 1931-[ca. 25 DEC 1932], 1931-1932; 3 (Reel 7)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 8.
  - 21 JAN 1933-22 SEP 1934, 1933-1934; 1 (Reel 8)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 9.
  - 3 OCT 1934-1 OCT 1935, 1934-1935; 2 (Reel 8)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 10.
  - 3 OCT 1935-21 FEB 1936, 1935-1936; 3 (Reel 8)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 11.
  - 2 MAR 1936-11936?], 4 (Reel 8)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 12.
  - 2 JAN 1937-31 AUG 1937, 1 (Reel 9)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 13.
  - 1 SEP 1937-28 FEB 1938, 1937-1938; 2 (Reel 9)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 14.
  - 1 MAR 1938-28 MAY 1938, 3 (Reel 9)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 15.
  - 2 JUN 1938-30 SEP 1938, 4 (Reel 9)
    Material from Box 2: Folder 16.
  - 3 OCT 1938-[post 1938?], 1 (Reel 10)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 1.
  - 2 JAN 1939-31 MAY 1939, 2 (Reel 10)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 2.
  - 3 JUN 1939-[post 1939], 3 (Reel 10)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 3.
  - [post 1 JAN 1940]-29 MAY 1940, 4 (Reel 10)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 4.
  - 4 JUN 1940-[post 1940], 1 (Reel 11)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 5.
  - 2 JAN 1941-30 JUN 1941, 2 (Reel 11)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 6.
  - 9 JUL 1941-[ca. 1941-1945?], 3 (Reel 11)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 7.
  - 2 JAN 1942-18 JUN"1942, 4 (Reel 11)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 8.
  - 3 JUL 1942-28 DEC 1942, 5 (Reel 11)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 9.
  - 4 JAN 1943-28 DEC 1943, 1 (Reel 12)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 10.
  - 4 JAN 1944-[ca. 1944-1945?], 2 (Reel 12)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 11.
  - 1 JAN 1945-[ca. 1945-1952?], 3 (Reel 12)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 12.
  - 17 JAN 1946-[1947], 4 (Reel 12)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 13.
  - 2 JAN 1948-26 APR 1950, 1948-1950; 1 (Reel 13)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 14.
  - 2 MAY 1956-[post 21 NOV 1952], 2 (Reel 13)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 15.
  - Correspondence, undated, 3 (Reel 13)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 16.
  - Memoranda, undated, 4 (Reel 13)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 17.
  - Biographical and membership material, 19 NOV 1912-[1952?], 5 (Reel 13)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 18.
  - Diary, 1 JAN 1919-10 APR 1919, 6 (Reel 13)
    Material from Box 3: Folder 19.
- Series II: Expense reports
  - Green, 1 MAY 1913-28 JAN 1914, 1913-1914; 7 (Reel 14)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 1.
  - Green, 22 FEB 1925-20 DEC 1933, 1925-1933; 8 (Reel 14)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 2.
  - Green, 26 JAN 1934-3 JAN 1939, 1934-1939; 9 (Reel 14)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 3.
  - Green, 20 FEB 1939-30 DEC 1943, 1939-1943; 10 (Reel 14)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 4.
  - Green, 4 FEB 1944-31 NOV 1951, 1944-1951; 11 (Reel 14)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 5.
  - Glenn, 3 MAR 1925-27 FEB 1945, 1925-1945; 12 (Reel 14)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 6.
- Series III: Speeches and statements
  - Green, notebook, [1919]-[ca. 1925-1932], 1919-1932; 13 (Reel 14)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 7.
  - Green, notebook, [16 JAN 1926]-[1926?], 14 (Reel 14)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 8.
  - Green, notebook, 19 MAR 1927-17 OCT [1928?], 1927-1928; 1 (Reel 15)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 9.
  - Green, notebook, 8 MAR 1929-[ca. 1930-1931], 1929-1931; 2 (Reel 15)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 10.
  - Green, notebook, [2 SEP 1931]- [1933?], 3 (Reel 15)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 11.
  - Green, notebook, [28 MAY 1934]-[post 1935], 1934-1935; 4 (Reel 15)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 12.
  - Green, notebook, 18 FEB 1936-4 AUG 1939, 1936-1939; 5 (Reel 15)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 13.
  - Green, notebook, 14 AUG 1940-[OCT 1942], 1940-1942; 6 (Reel 15)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 14.
  - Green, notebook, [1943?]-20 SEP 1951, 1943-1951; 7 (Reel 15)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 15.
  - Green, notebook, undated [ca. 1920s], 1920-1929; 1 (Reel 16)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 16.
  - Green, notebook, undated [ca. 1930s], 1930-1939; 2 (Reel 16)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 17.
  - Green, notebook, undated fragments, 3 (Reel 16)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 18.
  - Green, notebook, quotations, undated, 4 (Reel 16)
    Material from Box 4: Folder 19.
  - Green, other, [ore NOV 1920]-[pre DEC 1924], 1920-1924; 5 (Reel 16)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 1.
  - Green, other,.[post 1924J-18 DEC 1926, 1924-1926; 6 (Reel 16)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 2.
  - Green, other, JAN 1927-[pre 1934?], 1927-1934; 7 (Reel 16)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 3.
  - Green, other, 15 FER 1934-1937?], 1 (Reel 17)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 4.
  - Green, other, 11 FEB 1938-5 AUG 1940, 1938-1940; 2 (Reel 17)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 5.
  - Green, other, 12 MAY 1941-8 SEP 1952, 1941-1952; 3 (Reel 17)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 6.
  - Green, other, undated and undated fragments, 4 (Reel 17)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 7.
  - Probably Green, [post 1926]-[1950?], 5 (Reel 17)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 8.
  - Probably Green, undated and undated fragments, 1 (Reel 18)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 9.
  - Other individuals, Addes-Lee, JUN 1921-15 APR 1947, n.d., 1921-1947; 2 (Reel 18)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 10.
  - Other individuals, John L. Lewis, 3 APR 1922-OCT 1935, 1922-1935; 3 (Reel 18)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 11.
  - Other individuals, Lucchi-Wright, 15 MAY 1891-23 AUG 1949, n.d., 1891-1949; 4 (Reel 18)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 12.
  - AFL, 12 OCT 1926-12 APR 1944, 1926-1944; 5 (Reel 18)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 13.
  - Other organizations, 19,APR 1926-[1950?], 6 (Reel 18)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 14.
- Series IV: Subject files
  - American Federation of Actors, 18 JUL 1919, v [ca. 20 FEB 1939?]-[1939?], 1919-1939; 7 (Reel 18)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 15.
  - AFL Executive Council, 13 AUG 1919-9 JUL 1949, n. d., 1919-1949; 1 (Reel 19)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 16.
  - Agreements and contracts, 28 SEP 1925-16 FEB 1940, 1925-1940; 2 (Reel 19)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 17.
  - Communism, 1 APR 1926-27 SEP 1949, 1926-1949; 3 (Reel 19)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 18.
  - CIO, 29 SEP 1936-11 DEC 1944, 1936-1944; 4 (Reel 19)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 19.
  - CIO, [MAR 1936J-1 MAY 1941, 1936-1941; 5 (Reel 19)
    Material from Box 5: Folder 20.
  - Federation Bank and Trust Company, MAY 1923-30 SEP 1944, 1923-1944; 6 (Reel 19)
    Material from Box 6: Folder 1.
  - Federation Bank and Trust Company, 27 MAY 1932-8 DEC 1936, 1932-1936; 1 (Reel 20)
    Material from Box 6: Folder 2.
  - Federation Bank and Trust Company, 12 JAN 1937-9 DEC 1941, 1937-1941; 2 (Reel 20)
    Material from Box 6: Folder 3.
  - Federation Bank and Trust Company, 13 JAN 1942-27 MAR 1945, 1942-1945; 3 (Reel 20)
    Material from Box 6: Folder 4.
  - Injunctions, [1928], 4 (Reel 20)
    Material from Box 6: Folder 5.
  - National Broadcasting Company, [1926]-18.JAN 1942, 1926-1942; 1 (Reel 21)
    Material from Box 6: Folder 6.
  - Ohio State Office Building Commission, 7 MAR 1933-2 APR 1934, 1933-1934; 2 (Reel 21)
    Material from Box 6: Folder 7.
  - Joseph A. Padway, [FEB 1938]-8 OCT 1947, 1938-1947; 3 (Reel 21)
    Material from Box 6: Folder 8.
  - Politics, 10 AUG 1920-[1926], 1920-1944; 4 (Reel 21)
    Material from Box 6: Folder 9.
  - Progressive Mine Workers of America, 28 MAY 1937-[post APR 1944], 1937-1944; 5 (Reel 21)
    Material from Box 6: Folder 10.
  - United Mine Workers of America, 1912-[1 SEP 1952], 1912-1952; 6 (Reel 21)
    Material from Box 6: Folder 11.